DAN KLEIN: This is active
reinforcement learning.
You have to try things.
Sometimes, when you try
something, it's bad.
You get a negative reward,
and you keep on going.
You probably won't try that thing
again, but you paid the price.
In full reinforcement learning, we
would like to be able to compute
optimal policies like
value iteration did.
Now, of course, we're going to
make mistakes along the way.
That's going to a notion that we'll
talk about later, called regret.
But we'd like to eventually
learn the optimal thing.
So full reinforcement learning, we'd
like to produce optimal policies.
We still don't know the transition
or the rewards.
But now we're choosing the actions.
Our goal is to learn optimal things.
Eventually, we'd like to have the
optimal policy and the optimal values
in our hands.
In this case, the learner
is making choices.
And there's going to be a fundamental
trade-off of doing things that are
known to be pretty good, versus learning
about things like what
happens when I jump off the cliff.
That's a trade-off between what's called
exploration and exploitation,
which we'll talk about more later.
In order to do this, we need
to take a little detour.
In particular, let's remember back to
the algorithm we have for computing
optimal values.
What does it do?
We had value iteration.
It starts with a vector of zeros.
And it computes new approximations to
the values which converge to the
optimal values.
How did that work?
Well, what we do is we would take our
current values, Vk, and we do a layer
of expectamax from every state,
plugging those values in.
What's that layer of expectamax
look like?
It looks like how expectamax
always does.
We take a maximum over all of the
actions available from s.
We average all the outcomes.
And then, for each outcome, we compute
the utility as the instantaneous or
word plus the discounted future.
So this was correct.
Because it stuck a layer of expectamax,
that's a one layer of
optimality, on top of whatever
our old approximations were.
It buried those old approximations
under one layer of optimality.
We can't do this update with samples.
Why not?
We can't do this because
it's not an average.
And the only thing we can do with
samples is compute averages of things.
And why isn't this an average?
It's because there's a max.
And we don't of a way to use
samples to maximize.
The key idea here, in essence the
biggest advance in reinforcement
learning in decades, was a breakthrough
here where people
noticed, if you just shift down a half
a layer in the tree and look at the
expectamax recurrence from a chance
node, everything's different.
In particular, we know Q-values are
going to be useful, because it's
easier to choose actions for them.
And we can write down a version
of value iteration
that works with Q-values.
And let's think about
what it would be.
Well, we imagine we start out with some
approximation, Qk, which is the
Q-values in particular to depth k.
And so we think, all right, how am I
going to figure out the Q-value for
depth k plus 1 from some state,
s, and some action, a?
Well, if we knew the MDP and we had T
and we had R, we would say, all, right
what is this thing?
Well, let's think.
What happens at a chance node?
What happens is you have
some outcome s prime.
And for each outcome s prime, we have
to average together according to T,
the utility we will receive, if
this action leads to s prime.
Well, if this actually leads to s prime,
what utility will we receive?
We'll receive an instantaneous reward,
which is the reward of SaS prime.
And then we will receive a discount on
our future value from the landing
state, s prime.
And so I might be tempted to
write V of s prime here.
But I'm not learning values.
I'm learning Q-values, so I
need to do one more layer.
What is the value?
The value of the state is just the
maximum of all the Q-values going out
of that state.
And I have to maximize over all
of the actions that I could
take from that state.
So here it is.
It's almost exactly like the other
equation, but the recurrence has been
shifted a half a level.
The max is still there, right?
Here it is.
The average is still there.
There it is.
And there's still this flavor of taking
reward plus discounted future.
The critical difference here
is with this equation.
The thing in the front is an average.
This equation is an average.
And therefore, this equation
we can do with samples.
That gives rise to an algorithm
called Q-Learning.
So let's see Q-Learning.
And essentially, Q-Learning is this key
algorithm that allows us to do a
lot of great things with
reinforcement learning.
In Q-Learning, we're going to do Q-value
iteration, that is execute
this update where we replace a Q-value
with a one-step-look-ahead sample.
And we're going to do it as we go.
So every time we're in a state,
s, we take some action, a.
When we do that, we're going to learn
something about how good s, a is.
So what we're going to do is we're going
to maintain a table that looks
something like this.
For every state and every action, it's
going to maintain a number, which is
the Q-value approximation.
We're going to get some sample on the
basis of the action we picked.
The Q-Learning algorithm doesn't
actually care how
the action was chosen.
It does the same update, no
matter how it was chosen.
So what do we get?
We get a sample.
We were in s.
We chose action a.
And so we're going to learn something
about Q of s,a, that is, how good is
this action from this state?
We landed in s prime this time.
And we received reward r.
So what do we do?
Well, we consider, on one hand,
we have this old estimate.
On the basis of all of our past
experience, we are currently
estimating that action a from state
s is worth this value Q of s, a.
On the other hand, we've just received
some evidence from the world.
We've gotten the sample that says, on
the basis of this particular outcome,
it looks like what we're on track to
receive from s, a is the instantaneous
reward we just got, that's of
R of s, a, s prime, plus
the discounted future.
And the discounted future depends
on the s prime we land in.
And whatever s prime it is, we just
maximize overall of the a primes that
are possible from there.
So here is our discounted future.
All right, so on one hand, we have the
old estimate of how good Q of s, a is,
how good is this action
from this state.
On the other hand, we see what we're
on track to receive this time.
And we're going to balance them.
And it's just like before.
We're going to incorporate this new
sample estimate into the running
average by saying, mostly, we're going
to keep the old estimate, but with
some small weight we incorporate
this new sample.
And as we do this over and over again,
the samples, more or less, average
together where the recent ones
are up-weighted a little bit.
And we learn over time.
This is Q-Learning.
And it's pretty awesome what it does.
Let's take a look.
All right, first, I'm going
to execute it by hand.
So here is that cliff.
Everything on the bottom is bad.
And the exit on the right is good.
So watch as I go.
As I go, nothing really happens, until
I receive a non-zero reward.
And as I receive the exit from here,
in this case, it was plus 10.
And because my learning rate
is still set to 0.5--
which is not a good learning rate,
it's way too high, but it's
good for the demo--
if I keep doing this, we'll see that, as
I leave here I will learn something
about what east does from this state.
And you can see I update east.
The other actions haven't been updated,
because I didn't do them.
If I go here--
let's just do this for a while.
Let's build up some information
about going east.
So it looks like going
east is pretty good.
What happens if I jump off a cliff?
I learn that the fire pit is bad.
And if I do it again, I learn that
jumping off the cliff is bad.
[LAUGHTER]
DAN KLEIN: But I can do this all day
long, and I will never learn that the
start state is bad.
Why?
I guess the important thing here is,
when I move from here east, I land in
a state which has some good options
and some bad options.
But when I do my Q update,
I maximize over them.
And so I only incorporate that
9.8, not the negative 89.
So you can see that, even though I am
jumping off the cliff every time, in
fact, the east Q-values are going
up, because they look
at the optimal thing.
You can do that from
the start here too.
Let's look at the crawler
and its Q-values.
All right.
Ooh, flashy.
OK, do your best.
All right, so what's it doing?
Down here is, essentially,
the two angles it has.
And that's its action space.
This is its state space down here.
And I'm going to skip
a bunch of steps.
And now what you can see is green means
high Q-value over on the right
and high value over on the left.
And the little blue lines are
the currently optimizing
action for each state.
So if I turn off all randomness, you'll
see that what it's learned is
to execute the policy that's
shown in the Q-values.
And that gives rise to a small loop,
which gives it higher rewards, because
look at that thing trucking
off to the right.
There he goes.
Let's talk about the
properties of this.
There is an amazing result here.
Q-Learning, it looks just
like value learning.
It's not.
It's so much cooler
This is amazing.
Q-Learning will converge to the
optimal policy, even if you
do not follow it.
This is called off-policy learning.
You're doing whatever crazy
stuff you're doing.
And it's still learning optimal values,
even though you occasionally
jump off a cliff.
There's some caveats.
You have to explore enough, because
you're never going to learn about a
state or an action you don't visit.
You have to eventually make the
learning rate small enough.
But you can't make it decrease too
quickly, or eventually it will stop
learning things.
Basically, in the limit, it does not
matter how you select actions.
As long as you try lots of
stuff, you'll eventually
learn the right thing.
Now selecting actions poorly may incur
a large amount of regret, because you
jump off the cliff a little
more often than was wise.
But in the end, you will still learn
that cliff jumping is bad.
OK, next time we will talk about how to
select actions and what to do when
your state space is so large that you
can't keep a big table around.